Guide to the Rogers Family Papers 1614-1950 (bulk 1831-1950) MS 523
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Rogers Family Papers
1614-1950 (bulk 1831-1950)
MS 523
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
7.1 Linear feet (7 boxes)
The Rogers Family Papers depict the Civil War era sculptor John Rogers, Jr., his immediate family, and a lineage of ancestors. Materials of John Rogers, Jr. include personal correspondence, writings and drawings, travel papers, patents, ledger books, business contracts and correspondence, financial papers, journal clippings, and exhibition ephemera. The Rogers family papers include personal and business correspondence, ledger books, diaries, religious writings, and genealogical materials.
Provenance
Donation of Katherine R. Rogers, 1955.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading room for details.
Biographical Note
Born on October 30, 1829 in Salem, Massachusetts to Sara Ellen Derby and John Rogers, John Rogers, Jr. grew up in Cincinnati and rural Northampton, MA before the Rogers family moved to Roxbury, where he attended grammar school. In 1844 he entered the Boston English High School where he developed an interest and talent in drawing. However, as the descendent of a long lineage of Puritan ministers and merchants, pressure from his father and uncle led him to start a more practical career. After graduation in 1846, John Rogers, Jr. began work as a dry goods clerk in Boston and in 1848 took a position as a surveyor's assistant with the Boston Water Works, on the recommendation of his uncle Henry Bromfield Rogers, a Water Commissioner.
In December of 1848 John Rogers, Jr. suffered from a terrible cold and acute inflammation of the eyes that forced him to leave his job and seek treatment. He would make trips to Boston for entertainment, and there met a friend who first introduced him to clay modeling. While his eye-sight was so drastically impaired, Rogers turned to modeling for enjoyment. With little improvement in his eyes by July of 1849, his Grandmother Derby and uncle Henry Rogers sent him on a trip to Spain, where he spent more time sketching sights than recovering.
By July 1850 John Rogers, Jr. was well enough again to take a new position in a machine shop for the Amoskeag Corporation in Manchester, New Hampshire, where he worked until the fall of 1852. Then he moved to New York City to work at the Novelty Iron Works for a year before returning to his position in Manchester. By the winter of 1855-56, Rogers had become a Master Mechanic at the Amoskeag Machine Shop, and in April 1856 decided to move to Hannibal, Missouri to take a position as the Master Mechanic of the Hannibal and St. Joseph Rail Road. However, this job ended abruptly only a year and a half later during the Panic of 1857.
Throughout his years in the machinist trade, Rogers had continued to sculpt clay models and had created a number of small works. The sudden interruption of his career in 1857 quickly led to his decision to improve his skill by moving to Paris in September 1858 to study sculpture. However, discouraged by the minimal earnings of sculpture, in April 1859 Rogers returned home to the United States where a few months later in September he found a position at the surveyor's office of Chicago. He unexpectedly experienced his first success as a sculptor in a Charity Bazaar. His celebrated first piece, "Checkers at the Farm," was soon followed by "The Slave Auction," which took him to New York to finally start a career in sculpture.
In 1863 Rogers officially determined his business model of "large sales and small profits." During the years of the Civil War, Rogers, a Unionist, produced statues on contemporary topics and attained household renown. As Rogers' career took off, his studio in New York soon became a public showroom. His fame spread nationally from frequent reviews in newspapers, magazine, and trade journals. Some of his most notable pieces and subjects were statues of Gen. Reynolds, Henry Ward Beecher, Abraham Lincoln, Edwin M. Stanton, and Gen. Grant.
John Rogers, Jr. married Harriet Moore Francis in 1865, and together they had seven children, six of whom survived to adulthood: John, Katherine Rebecca, Charles Francis, Derby, Alexander Parker, and David Francis. Throughout his career Rogers was able to make a comfortable living. However after his retirement in 1894 and over thirty years of work, interest in his miniature group sculptures lessened. He moved permanently to his summer home in New Canaan, where he died in 1904.
The Rogers family's genealogy dates as far back as to the 16th century. Originally located in England, men of the Rogers family began a tradition of careers in the ministry. In 1636 Reverend Nathaniel Rogers moved the family to America, where the family took root in the surrounding areas of Boston and carried on the occupational tradition of Puritan ministers and New England merchants, providing their descendents with a respected family name. Though John Rogers, Sr. was also a merchant, he did not experience the same success and wealth that his predecessors had. However, in 1827, at the age of 27 Rogers married a 22 year-old Sarah Ellen Derby, daughter of the Salem banker John Derby. Together they had 7 children and moved several times in their early life, finally settling down in Roxbury, Massachusetts. John Rogers, Sr. and Sarah Ellen Derby remained close to Rogers, Sr.'s brother Henry Bromfield Rogers, a member of the Municipal Council and a Water Commissioner of Boston. H. B. Rogers played a significant role in the early life and career of John Rogers, Jr. providing connections and financial support when needed. The Rogers family was close and corresponded frequently amongst siblings and parents.
Source: Wallace, David H. John Rogers: The People's Sculptor. Middletown: Wesleyan UP, 1967.
Scope and Content Note
The Rogers Family Papers documents the family life and career of John Rogers, Jr. (1829-1904), the famous sculptor and former machinist, as well as Rogers family members dating back to the early 17th century. Notable ancestors included are Reverend John Rogers (1572-1636) of Dedham, Essex, descendant of the Martyr John Rogers and Reverend John Rogers (1630-1684), 5th President of Harvard University (1682-1684). Divided into two series, John Rogers, Jr. and the Rogers Family, the former consists of both personal and business letters, writings, drawings, and financial documents accumulated by John Rogers, Jr. through out his life. The latter series contains personal correspondence created or received by the immediate family members John Rogers, Jr. such as his sisters, father, or children. The second series also holds sermons, correspondence, and journals of Rogers family ancestors passed down from one generation to the next, and genealogical accounts, obituaries and timelines put together by later generations.
The letters of John Rogers, Jr. date back to his youth in Roxbury, Massachusetts and continue through his occupation as a machinist in New Hampshire, New York, and Missouri to his later career as a sculptor in New York City and New Canaan, Connecticut. As a sculptor of renown in the late 19th century, the correspondence of John Rogers, Jr. includes letters to and from some prominent figures, Henry Ward Beecher, Abraham Lincoln, Ulysses S. Grant, and Grover Cleveland. Rogers' sculptures often reflected themes of the Civil War which included and enthused some of these men, prompting notes of thanks and recognition. His lengthier communication with Henry Ward Beecher followed Rogers' 1860 exhibition of the first of a series of Civil War series called "The Slave Auction." The papers of John Rogers, Jr. additionally include personal writings and drawings that he created primarily in young adulthood, such as sketches from his trip to Spain in 1849 as well as animated short stories. John Rogers, Jr. also preserved important letters, contracts, and patents from his career as a sculptor. These records have been arranged in the last subseries and largely include correspondence relating to exhibitions of Rogers Groups and donations of statues by Rogers to museums and galleries.
The Rogers Family Papers consist of the correspondence of immediate family members of John Rogers, Jr., including his parents John Rogers, Sr. and Sarah Ellen Derby, siblings, most prominently Ellen Rogers, wife Harriet M. F. Rogers, and children, primarily Derby and Katherine R. Rogers. The family correspondence is largely comprised of communication between family members, but also in the case of Derby and Katherine R. Rogers, business correspondence relating to the Rogers Groups after their father's death. Rogers Family Papers also consist of the letters, diaries and sermons of ancestors, many of whom were Protestant religious leaders. The final subseries of the collection contains genealogical records collected by the younger generation of the Rogers family. Included are notes and letters, timelines, a scrapbook, and an extensive hand-written timeline dating back to the 15th century.
Arrangement
The records are organized into the following 3 series:
Series I: John Rogers, Jr.
Series II: Rogers Family
Series III: Photocopies of Rogers Family Documents
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Further materials about John Rogers, Jr. are located at the New-York Historical Society within the John Rogers Photograph Collection. Within the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections, additional images of John Rogers and Rogers family members are available in the Cased Photograph File (PR 012), certificates given to Rogers at various exhibitions are in the Certificate File (PR 014), a 1939 calendar showing Rogers sculpture groups is located in the Calendar File (PR 146) and an album containing photographs of Rogers and his sculpture groups is availablein the Album File (PR 002-12). Bronze masters and plaster Rogers Groups are available for study in the Henry Luce III Center of The New-York Historical Society.
Amoskeag Manufacturing Company.; Bromfield family.; Channing, William Ellery, 1780-1842.; Cleveland, Grover, 1837-1908; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Jewett, Catherine Rebecca, 1810-1841.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865; Perry, Martha Rogers, 1840-1925.; Rogers family.; Rogers, Alexander Parker, 1874-?.; Rogers, Charles Francis, 1870-1947.; Rogers, Clara Kathleen, 1844-1931.; Rogers, Daniel Denison, 1751-1825.; Rogers, Daniel, 1707-1785; Rogers, David Francis, 1876-1943.; Rogers, Derby, 1871-1955.; Rogers, Ellen Derby, 1828-1894.; Rogers, Harriet Francis, 1841-1927.; Rogers, Henry B. (Henry Bromfield), 1802-1887; Rogers, John, 1572?-1636; Rogers, John, 1630-1684; Rogers, John, 1666-1745; Rogers, John, 1800-1867.; Rogers, John, 1829-1904; Rogers, Katherine Rebecca, 1863-1956.; Rogers, Laura Derby, 1834-1907.; Rogers, Nathaniel, 1598-1655; Rogers, Sarah Ellen Derby, 1805-1877.; Thomas, Eunice B.; United States Sanitary Commission.; Whitefield, George, 1714-1770.; Account books.; Albums.; Clippings.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Drawings.; Hannibal (M.O.); New York (N.Y.); Passports.; Patents.; Roxbury (M.A.); Sculpture--1850-1900.; Sermons.; Sketches.; Spain -- Description and travel.; Textile machinery -- United States.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
- Series I: Papers of John Rogers, Jr., 1837-1941
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes all papers created by and about John Rogers, Jr. They are arranged in three subseries that make up his personal correspondence, letters and records related to his work as a sculptor, and additional creative writings and drawings that John Rogers, Jr. created during his lifetime.
  - Subseries I: Personal Correspondence, 1837-1904
    This subseries primarily consists of letters written by John Rogers, Jr. dating from adolescence up until his death in 1904. John Rogers wrote mainly to siblings, particularly sister Ellen Derby Rogers, his parents John Rogers, Sr. and Sarah Ellen Derby Rogers, and later in life to his children and wife Harriet Moore Francis Rogers. Also included is correspondence from a few notable Americans who wrote to John Rogers, Jr. about his work, including Abraham Lincoln, Ulysses S. Grant, Grover Cleveland, and Henry Ward Beecher. The letters are arranged chronologically.
    Rogers' earliest letters date back to his time at grammar school in Roxbury and the Boston English High School. The letters reflect day to day life, occasionally revealing an early interest in the arts. Later letters from Manchester, New Hampshire describe his first exploits in machinery and plan to develop a career as a machinist when he later writes from Hannibal, Missouri as a Master Mechanic. Rogers wrote fewer letters during his times abroad, but returns to Chicago and New York to write many letters about his unexpected success as an artist. His letters also include the many he wrote to wife Harriet Moore Francis Rogers following their marriage in 1865.
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1837-1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1850-1852 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1853-1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1856-1857 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1858-1859 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1861 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1862 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1864-1866 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1872-1878 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., 1880-1894 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Jr., Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, To John Rogers, Jr., 1837-1873 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, To John Rogers, Jr., 1880-1904 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, To John Rogers, Jr., Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, Abraham Lincoln to John Rogers, Jr., 1864 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, Ulysses S. Grant to John Rogers, Jr., 1868 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, Grover Cleveland to John Rogers, Jr., 1890 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, John Rogers to Harriet Moore Francis Rogers, 1865-1873 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, John Rogers to Harriet Moore Francis Rogers, 1874-1893 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Other Correspondence - 2 Items, 1882-Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II: Drawings and Writings, 1849-1858
    Included are drawings of work and travels created by John Rogers, Jr. during his young adulthood, as well as poetry and prose both apart from and about his sculpture. While at the Amoskeag Corporation in New Hampshire, Rogers filled a notebook with sketches of the various machinery he used and found in the Machine Shop. Rogers' trip to Spain in 1849 due to lingering illness and inability to work produced a number of sketches of sights, such as Gibraltar and the Alhambra. The travel journal documents his daily activities, his sometimes animated experiences on board the ship, and his encounters with Spanish natives and cultural events. The creative writings of John Rogers, Jr. include short stories and poems complemented with drawings as well as numerous copies of press releases for his sculpted groups.
    - Drawings of Machinery from Machine Shops of the Amoskeag Corporation, Manchester, N.H., 1854-1855 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Passport, Travel Journal, Sketches and Map from Trips to Spain and Cienfuegos, 1849-1858 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Poems and Writings by John Rogers, Jr., Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Subseries III: Business Papers, 1848-1971
    This subseries is comprised of John Rogers, Jr.'s patents of the Rogers Groups, ledger books, bills, business correspondence, papers and articles written about his Groups, and ephemera of past exhibitions of his statues. Business papers and documents include communication about upcoming exhibitions of his works, contracts of sale or donation to the Corcoran Gallery, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and many other lesser known institutions, and a draft notice for the army addressed to John Rogers, Jr. just months before the end of the Civil War in 1865. The writings on John Rogers' Groups contain a lecture by Frank Adams and a collection of poems by admirer Elizabeth Schip. These materials are arranged chronologically.
    - Constitution and statements, National Academy of Design, 1865, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Cabinet cards, Muybridge's photographic studies of horses in motion, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Patents of Rogers Groups, 1874-1888 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ledger Book and Bills, 1848-1908 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Business Papers & Correspondence, 1864-1905 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Descriptive catalogs and price lists, Rogers Statuette Groups, 1888, 1892, 1894, 1895, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Exhibitions and Advertisments, 1928-1937, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Certified Valuation List; Collectors Guide, 1946, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Exhibition Ephemera, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Lecture and poems about Rogers Groups, 1941, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper & Journal Articles about John Rogers, Jr., 1872-1876 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Articles about John Rogers and his statuary, 1910-1935, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Articles about John Rogers and his statuary, 1872-1887 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Essex Institute Historical Collections, Vol 53, Oct 1917 (includes article about John Rogers)(4 copies) (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
    - Biographical extracts of writing about John Rogers Jr; Documents relating to his works (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II: Papers of the Rogers Family, 1636-1950
  This series is comprised of three subseries. The first two contain the correspondence, diaries, poetry, prose, religious writings and financial papers of the immediate family of John Rogers, Jr. and Rogers family ancestors. The last subseries includes the genealogical records of the long lineage of the Rogers family collected and created by John Rogers, Jr.'s children and other unidentified family members.
  - Subseries I: John Rogers, Jr. Family Papers, 1848-1971
    This subseries consists primarily of correspondence, but also diaries, pictures, and financial documents created or received by immediate family members of John Rogers, Jr. This chiefly includes his children Alexander Parker, David Francis, Derby Francis, wife Harriet M. F. Rogers, father John Rogers, Sr., mother Sarah Ellen Derby Rogers, and siblings. Correspondence and personal papers are arranged alphabetically by folder and chronologically within each folder and subject. Many of the family members have just a few records included in the collection. However, those featured more prominently are Derby Francis Rogers, Harriet Moore Francis Rogers, Katherine R. Rogers, and John Rogers, Sr. Derby F. Rogers and sister Katherine R. Rogers both received and wrote much correspondence about their father's work after he passed, supplying information for exhibitions and signing legal contracts of sale or donation. Additionally, both brother and sister heavily pursued knowledge of their ancestry after John Rogers, Jr.'s death in 1904.
    The correspondence of Harriet Moore Francis Rogers (often called Hattie) is largely comprised of letters to and from her mother, Catherine Rebecca Jewett Francis, sisters-in-law, and friends. Harriet M. F. Rogers' diary includes favored quotes by various poets and authors. The correspondence of John Rogers, Sr. most prominently includes letters written to his wife Sarah Ellen Derby (often referred to as Ellen), and the letters of John Rogers, Sr.'s family include communication amongst siblings and mother Sarah Ellen Derby.
    - Chares f. Rogers, 1932-1947 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - David Francis Rogers, 1898-1913 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - David F. Rogers, Address and Ledger Books, 1910-1933 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Derby Francis Rogers, 1898-1909 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Derby F. Rogers, 1911-1929 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Derby F. Rogers, 1933-1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Derby F. Rogers, 1941-1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Eunice Burr Thomas, 1828-1840 (Box 5A, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, From Harriet M. F. Rogers, 1865-1874 (Box 5A, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, To Harriet M.F. Rogers, 1870-1910 (Box 5A, Folder 3)
    - Diary of Harriet M. F. Rogers, 1898 (Box 5A, Folder 4)
    - Katherine R. Rogers, 1904-1950 (Box 5A, Folder 5)
    - Ledger Books of John Rogers, Sr., 1893-1898 (Box 5A, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, From John Rogers, Sr., 1837-1884 (Box 5A, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, John Rogers, Sr. Family, 1835-1884 (Box 5A, Folder 8)
    - Estate of John Gardiner Perry, 1927 (Box 5A, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence of John Rogers, Jr. Extended Family, 1899-1939 (Box 5A, Folder 10)
    - Alienated Envelopes, Undated (Box 5A, Folder 11)
    - Literary submissions of Derby Rogers (folder 1 of 2) (Box 5A, Folder 12)
    - Literary submissions of Derby Rogers (folder 2 of 2) (Box 5A, Folder 13)
  - Subseries II: Papers of Rogers Family Ancestors, 1636-1898
    Dating back to early 17th century in Dedham, England, this subseries contains the correspondence, poetry, and sermons of the Rogers' family's past relatives, many of whom were religious leaders of the Protestant church. Additionally included are newspapers preserved by family members from as early as 1723 and 19th century paper currency. This subseries is arranged by person and chronologically within each folder. Many of the documents included are extremely aged and fragile. These documents also include a number of sermon books and notebooks written or used by some of the eldest members of the Rogers ancestry, as well as a genealogical timeline of the Foxcroft Family, related through Anna Foxcroft who married Reverend Daniel Rogers in 1748, created in 1730.
    - Reverend John Rogers, Undated-1636 (Box 5B, Folder 1)
    - Reverend Nathaniel Rogers, 1718-Undated (Box 5B, Folder 2)
    - Reverend John Rogers, 1742 (Box 5B, Folder 3)
    - Daniel Denison Rogers, 1805-1825 (Box 5B, Folder 4)
    - Poetry Book of Catherine R. Jewett, 1826-1827 (Box 5B, Folder 5)
    - Foxcroft Family Records, 1730 (Box 5B, Folder 6)
    - Period Newspapers, 1723-1898 (Box 5B, Folder 7)
    - Confederate & United States Paper Currency, 1863-1875 (Box 5B, Folder 8)
    - Daniel Rogers Notebook, 1614 (Box 5B)
    - Daniel Rogers Hebrew Grammar, 1707-1783 (Box 5B)
    - Daniel Rogers Sermons 1 of 2, 1707-1785 (Box 5B)
    - Daniel Rogers Sermons 2 of 2, 1775 (Box 5B)
    - Daniel Rogers Diary, 1740-1751 (Box 5B)
  - Subseries III: Genealogical research, 1872 - 1965
    This subseries consists chiefly of genealogical information collected and produced by members of the Rogers family. The subseries includes genealogical notes, extracts of writings about Rogers family ancestors, numerous articles, magazines and publications relating to and written by Rogers family members, and copies of family tree charts. Also included is corresondence, predominantly of Derby Rogers, concering this genealogical research, and a range of articles and publications on the works of John Rogers, sculptor.
    - Letters between Alexander P. Rogers and others, 1920, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 1)